<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Institute for Freedom of Information &#187; FOI Tracker</title>
	<atom:link href="http://i-foi.org/feed/?cat=2" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://i-foi.org</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2015 10:29:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.org/?v=4.2.4</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Congress Action on FOI Tracker #6</title>
		<link>http://i-foi.org/performance-tracker/congress-action-on-foi-tracker-6/</link>
		<comments>http://i-foi.org/performance-tracker/congress-action-on-foi-tracker-6/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2015 10:15:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[FOI Tracker]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://i-foi.org/?p=184</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The FOI Bill is dead, FOI Practice Lives August 20, 2015 It is now nearly three months since the Committee Report on the FOI Bill was submitted to plenary for deliberation, and almost four weeks since the session of Congress resumed. Yet the FOI Bill has not moved one bit at the House of Representatives. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1>The FOI Bill is dead, FOI Practice Lives</h1>
<p>August 20, 2015</p>
<p><span style="text-align: justify; line-height: 1.5;"><a href="http://i-foi.org/home/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/FOI-IS-DEAD.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-188" src="http://i-foi.org/home/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/FOI-IS-DEAD.jpg" alt="FOI IS DEAD" width="799" height="172" /></a></span></p>
<p><span style="text-align: justify; line-height: 1.5;">It is now nearly three months since the Committee Report on the FOI Bill was submitted to plenary for deliberation, and almost four weeks since the session of Congress resumed. Yet the FOI Bill has not moved one bit at the House of Representatives.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Today, we give way to the statement of the Right to Know, Right Now! Coalition, declaring the FOI Bill dead, and announcing the shift of its advocacy focus to FOI Practice.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">The FOI Tracker rating plunges to zero.</p>
<p>&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
<h4 style="text-align: center;">The FOI Bill is dead, FOI Practice Lives</h4>
<h5 style="text-align: center;">Right to Know, Right Now! Coalition</h5>
<p style="text-align: center;">August 20, 2015</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">The FOI Bill is dead. We put the blame squarely on President Aquino and the leadership of the House of Representatives.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">From our years of campaigning for the passage of the FOI Act, this we know for certain: without decisive support from the President and the leadership of the House of Representatives, the bill will not pass.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Benigno S. Aquino III led us to believe that it will be different under his administration. On at least two occasions before he took his oath as President, he promised that the passage of the FOI bill will be among his administration&#8217;s priorities. In 2011, his government also joined the Open Government Partnership, a multilateral initiative led by the US that aims to secure concrete commitments from governments to scale up transparency, accountability and public participation. We thought that he would see the urgency of passing the FOI Bill as an essential condition for Daang Matuwid.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Aquino is turning out to be no better than his predecessor on FOI. Now entering into the final months of his term, the Philippines remains the only one of the eight founding members of OGP that has not enacted an FOI Act. For all his admistration&#8217;s breast beating about transparency, President Aquino has not mustered the political will to honor his campaign pact with the people to assure the passage of FOI. Instead, early in his term, the promise of support turned into ever-mutating Presidential concerns over the FOI bill. Even after his concerns were addressed in the consolidated versions that emerged in Congress, we have not seen credible proof of his personal push for the measure.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">The President&#8217;s last SONA was a perfect opportunity for him to show a determined and sincere effort to pass the FOI. But for the the sixth and final time, he chose not to do so. Instead, his spokespersons point to a single sentence on FOI buried in page 38 of the 43-page Budget Message. If it can be included in the budget message, why can&#8217;t it be said openly for all to hear in the 2-hour-long SONA?</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Not foreseeing decisive action from the President&#8217;s camp, what is difficult enough to accomplish at the House of Representatives has become even harder. We are witness to Speaker Belmonte&#8217;s repeated promises on FOI that is not matched by action. The Speaker, under the rules, is the political and administrative head of the House of Representatives. He is responsible for the overall management of the proceedings of the House. He is primarily responsible for preparing the legislative agenda for every regular session, with the view of ensuring the full deliberation and swift approval especially of priority measures. Yet on the ground the Speaker has not lifted a finger to give FOI a positive push. On the contrary, Majority Leader Neptali Gonzales, the Speaker&#8217;s chief enforcer, is already laying the basis for all excuses for FOI&#8217;s non-passage. We can almost hear the tired and disingenuous refrain, &#8220;we tried our best, but we lacked time&#8221;.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">The Right to Know. Right Now! Coalition, in its more than 15 years of campaigning for the passage of the FOI Act, has held forums, issued statements, ran pooled editorials, participated actively in the legislative process, held mass actions, launched signature campaigns, held advocacy runs, filed its own bill by way of Indirect Initiative, produced information materials, initiated dialogues, and coordinated work with allies in Congress and the executive. We confront the reality that our institutions, particularly the Presidency and Congress, are not ready to overcome their selfish fears and take the side of public interest on the issue of FOI.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Under these circumstances, the coalition feels it unfair to continue to burden our House FOI champions with the expectation to take political risks in order to overcome the leadership&#8217;s refusal to push for FOI. We thank them for their efforts to bring the FOI Bill to the point where it is clearly at the doorstep of the President and the House leadership. We will continue to provide assistance to them as best we could should they request for it, for whatever next moves they will decide to take.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">While the FOI bill again meets its death in the hands of a President and a House leadership reluctant to redistribute power or too arrogant to heed our call, our fight for an effective, working, and living FOI, lives on. It may take a different form, emphasis and strategy, but its essence will remain the same: we assert the right to information as a fundamental mechanism in the struggle for a rights-based governance with greater transparency and accountability, less corruption, broader and informed peoples participation, and development outcomes that are sustainable and just.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">For us this fight will now take the road of FOI Practice. In the past year, the coalition has already been systematizing the coordination and documentation of experience in our information requests relating to our respective advocacies. We will scale this up to include administrative and judicial interventions to address the problems that we thought Congress, with decisive push from the President, would address though a comprehensive and progressive legislation. In this fight we will also engage the constitutionally mandated independent accountability institutions, such as the Civil Service Commission, the Commission on Audit, and the Ombudsman.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Lastly, we will use FOI Practice to bring to the surface the real cause why our politicians have defaulted, copped out, or resisted the passage of the FOI Act all this time. As starting point, we are revisiting the 2007 to 2009 COA audit of PDAF. We demand that COA and the agencies that implemented the PDAF projects afford us access not just to the main audit report, but also to all the underlying paper trail to the transactions that COA has found anomalous, so that the people may fully see how we were defrauded of public funds.</p>
<h4 style="text-align: center;">Organizations:</h4>
<p style="text-align: center;">Nepomuceno Malaluan<br />
Co-Convener, Right to Know. Right Now! Coalition</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Malou Mangahas<br />
Executive Director, Philippine Center for Investigative Journalism</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Vincent Lazatin<br />
Executive Director, Transparency and Acoountability Network</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Annie Enriquez-Geron<br />
President, Public Services Labor Independent Confederation (PSLINK)</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Melinda Quintos de Jesus<br />
Executive Director, Center for Media Freedom and Responsibility</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Josua Mata<br />
Secretary General, Sentro ng mga Nagkakaisa at Progresibong Manggagawa (SENTRO)</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Eirene Jhone Aguila<br />
Chairperson, Aksyong Kabayanihan para sa Organisadong Pagbabago (ANGKOP)</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Most Rev. Rolando J. Tria Tirona, OCD, DD<br />
National Director, CBCP-Nassa</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Sixto Donato C. Macasaet<br />
Executive Director, Caucus of Development NGO Networks (CODE-NGO)<br />
Isagani R. Serrano<br />
President, Philippine Rural Reconstruction Movement</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Leonor M. Briones<br />
Lead Convenor, Social Watch Philippines</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Ana Maria R. Nemenzo<br />
National Coordinator, WomanHealth Philippines</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Rene Magtubo<br />
Chairperson, Partido ng Manggagawa</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Max M. de Mesa<br />
Chairperson, Philippine Alliance of Human Rights Advocates (PAHRA)</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Jenina Joy Chavez<br />
Coordinator, Action for Economic Reforms &#8211; Industrial Policy Team</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Gerry F. Rivera<br />
President, PAL Employees Association (PALEA)</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Rowena C. Paraan<br />
Chairperson, National Union of Journalists of the Philippines</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Samuel Cesar Gamboa<br />
Secretary General, Freedom from Debt Coalition</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Joseph Purugganan<br />
Philippine Program Coordinator, Focus on the Global South</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Elso Cabangon<br />
Filipino Migrant Workers Group</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Norman Cabrera<br />
President, Ang Kapatiran Party</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Rolando Ocampo<br />
Prudentialife Warriors Pilipinas, Inc.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Ellene A. Sana<br />
Executive Director, Center for Migrant Advocacy</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Jaybee Garganera<br />
National Coordinator, Alyansa Tigil Mina<br />
Aida F. Santos<br />
President, Women&#8217;s Education, Development, Productivity &amp; Research Organization (WeDpro), Inc.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Red Batario, Executive Director; Adelina Sevilla Alvarez, Program Director<br />
Center for Community Journalism and Development</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Sonny Melencio<br />
Chairperson, Partido Lakas ng Masa-PLM</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Michael Cagulada<br />
Executive Director, Group Foundation, Inc. (Cagayan de Oro City)</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Merci L. Angeles<br />
President, Peace Women Partners, Inc.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Corazon Fabros<br />
Co-Convener, STOP the War Coalition, Philippines</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Ricardo Reyes<br />
Katarungan</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Individuals:</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Gregorio T. Mariano, Jr.<br />
Member, US Pinoys for Good Governance; Member, Global Filipino Nation</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Floro R. Francisco<br />
Regional Consultant (Asia), LO-Norway</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Walter I. Balane<br />
Chair, Piniyalan 2013-2016 Reporting Governance Project; Acting Station Manager, DXBU-Bukidnon State University radio; President, Bukidnon Press Club</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Ma. Victoria R. Raquiza<br />
Assistant Professor, National College of Public Administration and Governance, UP</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Buenaventura B. Dargantes<br />
Professor of Socio-ecology, Visayas State University</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Dino Manrique<br />
Member, #ScrapPork Network (SPN)</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Louie Checa Montemar<br />
Faculty member, Political Science Department, De La Salle University</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Ma. Aurora Quilala<br />
National Advocacy Officer, PLCPD</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Cesar Guarin<br />
Convener, Takbo Na! Pilipinas</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Clarissa V. Militante<br />
Writer</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Fr. Robert Reyes</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Mercedes L. Fabros</p>
<ul style="display: none;">
<li>08-20-2015</li>
<li>0</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://i-foi.org/performance-tracker/congress-action-on-foi-tracker-6/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Congress Action on FOI Tracker #5</title>
		<link>http://i-foi.org/performance-tracker/congress-action-on-foi-tracker-5/</link>
		<comments>http://i-foi.org/performance-tracker/congress-action-on-foi-tracker-5/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2015 11:19:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[FOI Tracker]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://i-foi.org/home/?p=103</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Speaker&#8217;s support for FOI mere lip service July 26, 2015 At around the time that the Senate approved the FOI bill on Third Reading in March 2014, House Speaker Feliciano Belmonte boldly proclaimed: “Ang ipinangako ko talaga is during the 16th Congress. Bitayin ninyo ako kung matapos ito at hindi pa nakakapasa.” (See GMA News) [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1><strong>Speaker&#8217;s support for FOI mere lip service</strong></h1>
<p>July 26, 2015</p>
<h1><a href="http://i-foi.org/home/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/gonzales-belmonte.jpg"><img class="  wp-image-107 aligncenter" src="http://i-foi.org/home/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/gonzales-belmonte.jpg" alt="House Majority Leader Neptali Gonzales wih" width="421" height="315" data-wp-pid="107" /></a></h1>
<h1></h1>
<p>At around the time that the Senate approved the FOI bill on Third Reading in March 2014, House Speaker Feliciano Belmonte boldly proclaimed: “Ang ipinangako ko talaga is during the 16th Congress. Bitayin ninyo ako kung matapos ito at hindi pa nakakapasa.” (See <a href="http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/story/352040/news/nation/belmonte-renews-vow-foi-bill-to-pass-in-16th-congress" target="_blank">GMA News</a>)</p>
<p>Yet on the ground the Speaker has not lifted a finger to give FOI a positive push. The bill has advanced at the committee level through the efforts of the committee chair, house champions and FOI advocates, at times even with counter-signals from the House leadership.</p>
<p>One clear evidence of the Speaker&#8217;s lack of actual commitment to advancing the FOI bill was his failure to put the FOI on the agenda, even for just its sponsorship in plenary, before Congress went to recess last June. This despite the Committee chair and authors expressing readiness for the bill&#8217;s sponsorship and defense, and a letter of appeal from advocates.</p>
<p>The Speaker, under the rules, is the political and administrative head of the House of Representatives. He is responsible for the overall management of the proceedings of the House. He is primarily responsible for preparing the legislative agenda for every regular session, with the view of ensuring the full deliberation and swift approval especially of priority measures.</p>
<p>With the Speaker only paying lip service to FOI, the FOI Tracker rating goes down to 25. It will just be a matter of time for his chief enforcer, Majority Leader Neptali Gonzales II, to drive the final nail in the coffin of the FOI bill in the 16th Congress. (See <a href="http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/story/352040/news/nation/belmonte-renews-vow-foi-bill-to-pass-in-16th-congress" target="_blank">GMA News</a>)</p>
<p>When all excuses are said and done, we see the House of Belmonte no different from the House of Nograles on FOI.</p>
<h4><strong> </strong></h4>
<h4>links to related news:</h4>
<p><a href="http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/story/528126/opinion/commentary-2015-will-be-a-reckoning-of-promises-on-foi" target="_blank">2015 will be a reckoning of promises on FOI</a></p>
<p><a href="https://youtu.be/2PgvFTbF34w" target="_blank">BT: Freedom of Information bill, nakabinbin pa rin sa Kongreso</a></p>
<ul style="display: none;">
<li>07-26-2015</li>
<li>25</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://i-foi.org/performance-tracker/congress-action-on-foi-tracker-5/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Congress Action on FOI Tracker # 4</title>
		<link>http://i-foi.org/performance-tracker/congress-action-on-foi-tracker-4/</link>
		<comments>http://i-foi.org/performance-tracker/congress-action-on-foi-tracker-4/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2015 02:47:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[FOI Tracker]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://i-foi.org/home/?p=54</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Committee Chair, Authors and Champions Ready for Second Reading: Will the House Leadership Give Time for FOI? May 28, 2015 Today, we give way to the statement below by House Committee on Public Information Chairperson Rep. Jorge Almonte and the House FOI champions and authors. They released the statement yesterday during their briefing for the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Committee Chair, Authors and Champions Ready for Second Reading:</span><br />
Will the House Leadership Give Time for FOI?</h1>
<p>May 28, 2015</p>
<p>Today, we give way to the statement below by House Committee on Public Information Chairperson Rep. Jorge Almonte and the House FOI champions and authors. They released the statement yesterday during their briefing for the press at the House of Representatives.</p>
<p>The Chair and the authors expressed their readiness for Second Reading. The ball is now in the hands of Speaker Belmonte and Majority Leader Neptali Gonzales II, to give time for the sponsorship of FOI and to start the period of interpellation in plenary.</p>
<p>The FOI Tracker rating remains at 75, at the threshold of the Green Zone. Its movement will depend on the action of the House leadership in the coming two weeks before adjournment sine die.</p>
<h4>PRESS STATEMENT<br />
May 27, 2015<br />
&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8211;</h4>
<div id="attachment_57" style="width: 3850px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><a href="http://i-foi.org/home/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/DSC06805.jpg"><img class="wp-image-57 size-full" src="http://i-foi.org/home/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/DSC06805.jpg" alt="FOI House Champions during presscon" width="3840" height="2160" data-wp-pid="57" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">from left to right: Rep. Teddy Baguilat, Rep. Raul Del Mar, Rep. Jorge Almonte, Rep. Leah Pacquiz, Rep. Barry Guttierez, Rep. Anthony Bravo &#8211; Photo by: Cong Corrales (PCIJ)</p></div>
<h4>COMMITTEE REPORT ON FOI FILED<br />
COMMITTEE CHAIR, AUTHORS AND CHAMPIONS READY FOR SECOND READING</h4>
<p>THE COMMITTEE ON PUBLIC INFORMATION through the Deputy Secretary General for Committee Affairs on Monday (May 25) transmitted to the Deputy Secretary General for Operations the Committee Report on FOI. The committee report, now numbered as Committee Report No. 746 alongside the substitute FOI bill now numbered as House Bill No. 5801, consolidates twenty-three (23) FOI bills including one filed through Indirect Initiative by the Right to Know. Right Now! Coalition. This concludes the committee-level process, and marks its shift to plenary-level consideration.</p>
<p>&#8220;We are geared up for the Second Reading and Debate of the FOI Bill, pursuant to Rule X, Section 53 of the House Rules. As Chair of the principal sponsoring committee, I am ready for the main sponsorship and defense in interpellation of this measure at anytime it is put in the Calendar of Business,&#8221; declared Rep. Almonte.</p>
<p>Rep. Teddy Baguilat, an author and leading FOI champion, said that bill authors have been in regular consultation to discuss their support to the Chair on FOI&#8217;s Second Reading. &#8220;Even during the TWG process, the authors and champions actively met outside formal deliberations to facilitate consensus. We will continue doing this in preparation for plenary, including deciding on co-sponsorships and special assignments in interpellation as the Chair may designate,&#8221; Baguilat said.</p>
<div id="attachment_70" style="width: 3850px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><a href="http://i-foi.org/home/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/DSC06813.jpg"><img class="wp-image-70 size-full" src="http://i-foi.org/home/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/DSC06813.jpg" alt="DSC06813" width="3840" height="2160" data-wp-pid="70" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Photo by: Cong Corrales (PCIJ)</p></div>
<h4>Salient features of the FOI Bill</h4>
<p>Rep. Almonte said that a key objective of the bill is to lay down a uniform, definite and effective procedure for citizens to access official records, documents and papers pertaining to official acts, transactions, or decisions of government.</p>
<p>&#8220;The bill mandates all government agencies to comply with a citizen&#8217;s request for information within fifteen (15) working days. RA 6713 only requires agencies to respond, while the FOI bill goes further by requiring the actual release of the information within the period,&#8221; Almonte explained.</p>
<p>Rep. Emmeline Aglipay-Villar, a consistent champion of the bill, added that the bill gives the right to information much needed teeth by introducing specific grounds for administrative and criminal liability. &#8220;Under the bill, refusal to promptly forward a request, failure to act on the request within the required fifteen working days, claiming an exception that is manifestly devoid of factual or legal basis, refusal to comply with lawful decision to release information, and approval of policies, rules and regulations manifestly contrary to the bill&#8217;s provisions, are tantamount to gross neglect of duty. In addition, falsely denying or concealing the existence of information mandated for disclosure, and destroying records for the purpose of frustrating the requesting party’s access, are deemed to be criminal acts,&#8221; Aglipay said. (<a href="https://youtu.be/2m1PHGS8xx4" target="_blank">learn more about the FOI bill</a>)</p>
<p>For her part, Rep. Leni Robredo emphasized that the authors and the committee did not limit the FOI Bill to request-based access.</p>
<p>&#8220;We also included in the bill many supply driven aspects. This will mandate government to supply information without need of a request from a citizen or the public. For example, Section 9 provides a list of important documents that government needs to disclose proactively without need for request. Further strengthening the proactive disclosure mechanisms is the integration of Open Data standards. Section 25 requires government agencies to publish in the Open Data Philippines website datasets generated in the implementation of agency mandates, programs, activities, and projects. As much as practicable, the datasets shall be in machine-readable and open formats. These supply driven aspects of our FOI bill is a new innovation that came out from various consultations and discussions. This unique aspect enhances and sets this current version apart from the other FOI bills that have been filed before,&#8221; Robredo expounded.</p>
<h4>Reasonable exceptions</h4>
<p>One area of the bill that has generated controversy is the exceptions. Section 7 of the bill enumerates the limited grounds for government to withhold documents from citizens.</p>
<p>Rep. Almonte stressed that it is both a legal duty and a practical necessity for Congress to define the exceptions to the right to information. &#8220;It is recognized worldwide, and our Supreme Court agrees, that the right to information is not absolute. Our constitution assigned to Congress the authority to define the limitations, and it is very important that we discharge this duty properly in order to provide both government personnel and citizens clear guidelines on what information should be made accessible and what may be validly withheld. The reality is, in the absence of a definitive list of exceptions, there is wide latitude for government to set up exceptions, and citizens are left only with the recourse of challenging these before the courts on a case-by-case basis,&#8221; Almonte explained.</p>
<p>Rep. Gutierrez of Akbayan Party List attested that the TWG extensively discussed the exceptions to make sure they are reasonable and do not unduly limit the people&#8217;s right to information. &#8220;The TWG devoted nine meetings to deliberating the exceptions line-by-line. Not only did we make sure that each exception related to protecting an acceptable, legitimate and clearly stated public interest, we also adopted strong safeguards to counter any tendency to abuse exceptions. For example, the government agency has the burden of proving the legal and factual basis in claiming an exception. They cannot interpret the exceptions expansively; they must interpret them strictly. The exceptions cannot be invoked to cover-up a crime, wrongdoing, graft, or corruption. The President, the Supreme Court, the Senate, the House of Representatives, and the Constitutional Commissions may waive an exception with respect to information in their control when they deem that there is an overriding public interest in disclosure. Beyond the terms of the proposed measure, citizens are also not prevented from seeking judicial review to overcome a recognized exception by proving a compelling need for disclosure,&#8221; Gutierrez explained.</p>
<p>Rep. Magnolia Antonino recalled the kind of balancing of interests that the authors had to make to allow a consensus on the committee report to emerge. &#8220;My bill originally contained a provision exempting certain documents from mandatory disclosure. There were comments that this provision ran counter to certain laws. I readily proposed an amendment that removed the legal infirmity, but still recognized that even public officials also retain some level of privacy, though to a lesser extent than private individuals, and carefully balanced with the public interest in disclosure. I also recall that there were authors, such as Rep. Castelo, who withdrew their proposals for additional exceptions to facilitate consensus,&#8221; Antonino said.</p>
<div id="attachment_67" style="width: 3850px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><a href="http://i-foi.org/home/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/DSC06817.jpg"><img class="wp-image-67 size-full" src="http://i-foi.org/home/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/DSC06817.jpg" alt="DSC06817" width="3840" height="2160" data-wp-pid="67" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Photo by: Cong Corrales (PCIJ)</p></div>
<h4>A transformative measure</h4>
<p>Deputy Speaker Henedina Abad expressed her belief that the FOI Act will be a transformative measure for the country. &#8220;While the scrutiny of the bills at the committee level centered on the specific provisions of the measure, my commitment to the immediate passage of the FOI bill is foremost animated by what having an FOI law represents. I think it goes beyond the techniques and best practices in an FOI law &#8212; it is also political. I firmly believe that having a working FOI Act will be a key element in building a culture of transparency and accountability in the country. I say &#8220;culture&#8221; to emphasize the importance of an FOI Act not just as a legal document, but as a mechanism that will contribute to developing a way of life in both thinking and action for government and citizens alike,&#8221; Abad said.</p>
<p>&#8220;It is because of the positive transformative impact an FOI Act will have for the country that I support its passage as much as I support the improvement of higher education,&#8221; Rep. Roman Romulo agreed.</p>
<p>Rep. Anthony Bravo and Cresente Paez of Coop-Natcco Party List said that the FOI is in support of the Aquino administration&#8217;s commitment of &#8220;Tuwid na Daan&#8221;. &#8220;This bill will provide a lifeblood to both the advocacy of President Aquino and that of the leadership of Congress to adhere to the principles of good governance. FOI is in fact a realization of the aspiration of the people for change and transparency in government,&#8221; Bravo said.</p>
<p>Rep. Winnie Castelo added that while an FOI law is foremost a human right measure, the country&#8217;s leaders should not overlook the fact that it is also an economic measure. &#8220;The recent strong economic performance is based to a considerable degree on the favorable perception by the international and local business community of the current administration&#8217;s good governance and anti-corruption initiatives. An FOI law will institutionalize these initiatives and help minimize uncertainties in political transition. The FOI law will support a political environment conducive to growth and development,&#8221; Castelo said.</p>
<p>Rep. Kaka Bag-ao qualified that an FOI Law is a measure that will benefit all Filipinos, not just citizens but also public officials. &#8220;FOI is a measure that will ultimately benefit legislators who walk the straight and narrow path. In the context of governance, it is essential for us public officials to gain and sustain trust from citizens. A government that enjoys high trust from the people is able to carry out its programs more effectively, including in the districts that we represent in Congress,&#8221; Bag-ao said.</p>
<div id="attachment_73" style="width: 3850px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><a href="http://i-foi.org/home/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/DSC06811.jpg"><img class="wp-image-73 size-full" src="http://i-foi.org/home/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/DSC06811.jpg" alt="DSC06811" width="3840" height="2160" data-wp-pid="73" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Rep. Gus Tambunting- Photo by: Cong Corrales (PCIJ)</p></div>
<h4>Next steps</h4>
<p>Rep. Gus Tambunting appealed to his colleagues in Congress across party lines persuasions to already manifest their express support for the committee report. &#8220;I appeal to all our colleagues, across party lines and persuasions, to support the committee report and take the bold step to advance the immediate approval of the bill in plenary.&#8221;</p>
<p>Rep. Leah Paquiz of Ang Nars also called on party list members to likewise express support for the committee report. &#8220;FOI is an issue of sectors that are marginalized and under-represented, and I hope party list representatives will collectively add their voice and vote for the approval of the FOI committee report in plenary,&#8221; Paquiz said.</p>
<p>Rep. Raul Del Mar, a co-author of the bill in the 14th Congress and a principal author in the current Congress, said that this 16th Congress has a unique opportunity to fulfill a duty to the people by completing the final enactment into law of this FOI bill which has been filed and re-filed since the 8thCongress twenty-eight years now. “I am hopeful that our esteemed colleagues under the leadership of Speaker Belmonte will seize the moment and ensure the approval on third reading of the measure, as well as the ratification of the bicameral conference committee thereon, before our Christmas break.”</p>
<p>Deputy Speaker Abad and Chair Almonte expressed confidence that Speaker Belmonte and the House leadership will promptly give due course to the FOI bill in plenary in the coming days.</p>
<p>As of end 2014, 103 countries already have an FOI law.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h4>links to related news:</h4>
<p><a href="http://www.philstar.com/headlines/2015/05/26/1458852/house-debates-foi-bill-start-soon" target="_blank">House debates on FOI bill to start soon</a></p>
<p><a href="http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/694080/passage-of-decades-old-foi-bill-by-december-doable-solon-says" target="_blank">Passage of decades-old FOI bill by December doable, solon says</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/story/493018/news/nation/house-foi-bill-seen-making-it-to-second-reading-before-congress-adjourns-june-10" target="_blank">House FOI bill seen making it to Second Reading before Congress adjourns June 10</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.sunstar.com.ph/manila/local-news/2015/05/25/house-panels-submit-committee-report-foi-409373" target="_blank">House panels submit committee report on FOI</a></p>
<ul style="display: none;">
<li>05-28-2015</li>
<li>75</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://i-foi.org/performance-tracker/congress-action-on-foi-tracker-4/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Congress Action on FOI Tracker # 3</title>
		<link>http://i-foi.org/performance-tracker/congress-action-on-foi-tracker-3/</link>
		<comments>http://i-foi.org/performance-tracker/congress-action-on-foi-tracker-3/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2015 15:21:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[FOI Tracker]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://i-foi.org/home/?p=50</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[House FOI Committee Report Filed! May 25, 2015 Today, May 25, 2015, the House Committee on Public Information filed the Committee Report on FOI. We now have the numbered committee report and substitute FOI bill: Committee Report No. 746 and House Bill No. 5801. The next step will be for the Second Reading and Debate [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1>House FOI Committee Report Filed!</h1>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5;">May 25, 2015</span></p>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5;">Today, May 25, 2015, the House Committee on Public Information filed the Committee Report on FOI. </span></p>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5;">We now have the numbered committee report and substitute FOI bill: Committee Report No. 746 and House Bill No. 5801. </span></p>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5;">The next step will be for the Second Reading and Debate on the FOI Bill in plenary. </span><span style="line-height: 1.5;">As we noted in our FOI Tracker # 2, we have reached the critical stage where high prioritization by the leadership of Congress and by President Aquino is imperative for FOI to finally pass. </span></p>
<div id="attachment_62" style="width: 910px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><a href="http://i-foi.org/home/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/committeereport.png"><img class="size-full wp-image-62" src="http://i-foi.org/home/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/committeereport.png" alt="Committee Report" width="900" height="1014" data-wp-pid="62" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Committee Report</p></div>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5;">For the moment, however, we pause to recognize the hard work that allowed the bill to advance to this stage. We thank Committee Chairperson Rep. Jorge Almonte, the House FOI champions and authors across political parties coordinated by Rep. Teddy Baguilat and Rep. Kaka Bag-ao, key administration allies in Congress led by Deputy Speaker Henedina Abad and Rep. Leni Robredo, and all their legislative officers as well as the staff of the Committee Secretariat. Pushing the bill through the committee process was not easy; it entailed a lot of committed work, strategizing and execution. </span></p>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5;">The FOI Tracker rating moves up to 75, the threshold of the Green Zone. With the limited time left, we still hope that the bill will be sponsored, and interpellation started, before the Congress recess on June 12. This will move FOI back into the Green Zone.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<ul style="display: none;">
<li>05-25-2015</li>
<li>75</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://i-foi.org/performance-tracker/congress-action-on-foi-tracker-3/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Congress Action on FOI Tracker # 2</title>
		<link>http://i-foi.org/performance-tracker/congress-action-on-foi-tracker-2/</link>
		<comments>http://i-foi.org/performance-tracker/congress-action-on-foi-tracker-2/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2015 02:33:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[FOI Tracker]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://i-foi.org/home/?p=45</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[FOI Losing Time, High Prioritization Essential May 23, 2015 COMMITTEE ON PUBLIC INFORMATION Chairperson Jorge T. Almonte and House FOI champions and authors were scheduled to file the Committee Report on the FOI Bill with the Secretary General of the House of Representative last Wedneday, May 20, at 3:30 pm. However, at around 2:00 pm, Chair [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1><strong>FOI Losing Time, </strong><strong>High Prioritization Essential</strong></h1>
<p>May 23, 2015</p>
<p>COMMITTEE ON PUBLIC INFORMATION Chairperson Jorge T. Almonte and House FOI champions and authors were scheduled to file the Committee Report on the FOI Bill with the Secretary General of the House of Representative last Wedneday, May 20, at 3:30 pm. However, at around 2:00 pm, Chair Almonte felt compelled to postpone the event, anticipating that the final vote on the BBL happening that afternoon will take longer than earlier expected. He was set to vote on the BBL, along with a number of FOI authors who are members, ex-officio members, or deputized members of the House Ad Hoc Committee on the Bangsa Moro Basic Law.</p>
<p>We hope that the postponed filing of the Committee Report on the FOI Bill will happen at the soonest. The filing of the report is significant. It marks the shift of the FOI Bill from the committee level to the even more challenging work at the plenary level.</p>
<p>In spite of the advance of the FOI bill signified by the filing of the Committee Report, we lost important time. The last three weeks since the resumption of session on May 4, and early next week when the BBL goes through approval by the Committee on Appropriations, would have been an opportunity to start sponsorship and interpellation of the FOI bill in plenary.</p>
<h4><strong>The Need for High Prioritization</strong></h4>
<p>This brings to light the importance of a measure being given high prioritization by the leadership of Congress and by the President. The impact of high prioritization on how a measure moves in Congress, particularly for major, controversial or resisted bills like FOI, is all too clear. We saw it in RH, in Sin Tax, and now in BBL.</p>
<p>We attest to the hard work at the committee level of Chair Almonte, FOI authors and champion legislators and their staff, as well as of the advocates in getting the bill through the committee process. We attest to the responsiveness of the Committee on Appropriations and its Chairperson, Rep. Isidro Ungab, in the prompt approval of the appropriations provision of the bill. We also attest to the committed and untiring support from the staff of the committee secretariat. (<em>See legislative history of the FOI bill at the committee level in 16th Congress below</em>).</p>
<p>However, this is where high prioritization spells the difference. To be sure certain steps could have been speeded up if the passage of FOI is given high priority, similar to the bills we mentioned earlier.</p>
<p>Especially at this critical juncture when we approach the third and final regular session in a Presidential election year, the FOI bill cannot be just one of numerous priorities. It will take a very high level of prioritization and leadership if it is to finally pass.</p>
<p>By observation we are all familiar with the many mechanisms by which a high level of prioritization is conveyed: a high-level meeting, a phone call, adoption of a clear timetable, clearing-up of hold-ups and delays, mention at the State of the Nation Address, the President certifying to the necessity of immediate enactment, and ultimately, the House leadership putting the bill on the plenary agenda and mobilizing key legislators to move the process forward.</p>
<p>The coalition sees it as a challenge for itself and concerned citizens to demonstrate a compelling strength to move our leaders to place the passage of the FOI Bill high in their priorities, as much as we see it as a matter of accountability and question of leadership for the highest leaders of this country.</p>
<h4><strong>FOI Tracker Rating Drops</strong></h4>
<p>In our FOI Tracker # 1 assessing Congress action on FOI, we said that the bill was well positioned for passage, and in the Green Zone with a rating of 85.</p>
<p>With the delay and anticipating that the BBL will reach plenary given its prioritization, our appeal for the completion of sponsorship and start of interpellation before the June 11 adjournment has turned difficult. Given this, the rating drops by 20 points to 65, and moves to the Yellow Zone. The FOI Tracker may be viewed at <a href="http://www.i-foi.org">http://www.i-foi.org</a></p>
<h4><strong>Legislative History of the FOI Bill at the Committee Level in the 16th Congress</strong></h4>
<table style="height: 1079px;" width="429">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td width="121">October 23, 2013</td>
<td width="317">Committee organizational meeting, where a motion to create a Technical Working Group (TWG) to consolidate the FOI bills was approved</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="121">November 26, 2013</td>
<td width="317">The TWG was constituted</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="121">February 6, 2014</td>
<td width="317">TWG Meeting # 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="121">February 18, 2014</td>
<td width="317">TWG Meeting # 2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="121">March 10, 2014</td>
<td width="317">TWG Meeting # 3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="121">May 12, 2014</td>
<td width="317">TWG Meeting # 4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="121">May 19, 2014</td>
<td width="317">TWG Meeting # 5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="121">May 28, 2014</td>
<td width="317">TWG Meeting # 6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="121">June 9, 2014</td>
<td width="317">TWG Meeting # 7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="121">August 4, 2014</td>
<td width="317">TWG Meeting # 8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="121">September 2, 2014</td>
<td width="317">TWG Meeting # 9, Approval of Substitute Bill</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="121">November 24, 2014</td>
<td width="317">Committee Approval of the Substitute BillVoting:Nine (9) Yes:     Reps. Abad, Aglipay-Villar, Baguilat, Bataoil, Bello, Dalog, Ferriol-Pascual, Gutierrez, Lobregat, PaquizThree (3) No:   Reps. Colmenares, Romualdo, Tinio</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="121">November 25, 2014</td>
<td width="317">Referral to the Committee on Appropriations for approval of the appropriations provision of the Substitute Bill</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="121">March 4, 2015</td>
<td width="317">Approval of the appropriations provision, with amendment, by the Committee on Appropriations</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="121">March 24, 2015</td>
<td width="317">Certification of Committee on Appropriations action received by the Committee on Public Information</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="121">May 14, 2015</td>
<td width="317">Committee Secretariat receives back the documentation of the Committee Report from the 4-step administrative approval by the Committee Affairs Department of the House Secretariat, through the Service Director, Deputy Executive Director, Executive Director and the Deputy Secretary General for Committee Affairs</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="121">May 19, 2015</td>
<td width="317">Committee Report signed by Rep. Isidro Ungab on the part of the Committee on Appropriations. Rep. Jorge Almonte, FOI authors and champions agree to a group filing of the Committee Report on May 20, 2015 at 3:30 pm, upon signing of the committee report by Rep. Jorge Almonte on the part of the Committee on Public Information</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="121">May 20, 2015</td>
<td width="317">Scheduled group filing of the Committee Report with the Secretary General postponed</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The FOI Tracker has a meter assessing Congressional action. The Green Zone between 75 to 100 points denotes good performance by Congress. The yellow zone between 50 to 75 points denotes performance that needs improvement, but still with optimistic outlook on the bill. The Red Zone between 25 to 50 points denotes bad performance and pessimistic prognosis on the bill. The Black Zone between 0 to 25 points denotes that the 16th Congress is evidently again out to kill the FOI Bill.</p>
<ul style="display: none;">
<li>05-23-2015</li>
<li>65</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://i-foi.org/performance-tracker/congress-action-on-foi-tracker-2/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Congress Action on FOI Tracker # 1</title>
		<link>http://i-foi.org/performance-tracker/congress-foi-performance-tracker-1/</link>
		<comments>http://i-foi.org/performance-tracker/congress-foi-performance-tracker-1/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2015 16:51:52 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[FOI Tracker]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://i-foi.org/home/?p=7</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[FOI Bill Well Positioned for Passage; Citizens to Track Congress Action on FOI May 12, 2015 Congress resumed session on May 4, 2015, with the proposed People&#8217;s Freedom of Information Act well positioned for passage. After months of deliberation by a Technical Working Group, the House Committee on Public Information approved (9 votes in favor, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1>FOI Bill Well Positioned for Passage; Citizens to Track Congress Action on FOI</h1>
<p>May 12, 2015</p>
<p>Congress resumed session on May 4, 2015, with the proposed People&#8217;s Freedom of Information Act well positioned for passage.</p>
<p>After months of deliberation by a Technical Working Group, the House Committee on Public Information approved (9 votes in favor, 3 against) on November 24, 2014 a consolidated version of 24 FOI bills. On March 5, 2015, the House Committee on Appropriations approved the appropriation provision of the bill.</p>
<p>This paves the way for the House plenary process on the FOI bill to begin. If approved on Second and Third Reading, the bill will be reconciled with the Senate version already approved on Third Reading and awaiting the House counterpart version as early as March 2014.</p>
<h4>Timetable a matter of commitment and leadership</h4>
<p>While the FOI bill is well positioned for passage, Congress will be working within a very tight timetable.</p>
<p>Only four weeks remain of the second regular session that ends on June 11. Congress and the Executive have enrolled the passage of the Bangsamoro Basic Law or BBL as their top legislative priority during the period. After adjourning on June 12, Congress will only resume session on July 27, when President Aquino will deliver his last state of the nation address. The FOI bill will then have to compete for time with other pending measures, foremost of which will be the 2016 budget. By the time of filing of candidacy in October 2015, legislators and other elected officials will also expectedly devote increasing attention to electoral matters.</p>
<p>These time limitations are apart from the political resistance that the FOI bill has historically faced.</p>
<p>Given our experience with FOI in past Congresses, we believe it is imperative that Congress is able to ratify a Bicameral Conference Committee Report before Congress goes on recess in December 2015, if we are to see the FOI Bill passed into law within the term of President Aquino and the 16th Congress.</p>
<p>According to this timetable, we believe it necessary that the bill is sponsored and the period of interpellation be started substantially during the session from May 4 to June 11. It is crucial for the period of interpellation to start immediately, in order to allow sufficient time for the committee, authors, and advocates to address any remaining issues that may surface.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: 20px; font-weight: bold; line-height: 1.2;">Congress Action on FOI Tracker</span></p>
<p>The Right to Know. Right Now! Coalition will monitor the action of Congress on FOI in the coming days, weeks, and months.</p>
<p>We have set up an online <strong>Congress Action on FOI Tracker</strong> (http://i-foi.org) that will provide the public with timely and regular updates on the status of the FOI Bill.</p>
<p>The <em>FOI Tracker</em> will also provide a periodic assessment of Congressional commitment on the passage of the FOI Bill. The assessment will be based on the substantive quality and integrity of the bill in terms of the people’s right to information. It will also track Congressional action based on the following timetable:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>May 4 to June 11, 2015 Session</strong> – Second Reading and Debate should commence in the House of Representatives, with Sponsorship completed and Period of Interpellation substantially started by Adjournment Sine Die.</li>
<li><strong>July 25, 2015</strong>, when Third Regular Session of Congress starts – The continuation of Period of Interpellation must be calendared immediately.</li>
<li><strong>September 2015</strong> – Period of Interpellation or Debate must have been closed or terminated.</li>
<li><strong>October 2015</strong> – Period of Amendments must have been completed.</li>
<li><strong>November 2015</strong> – The People’s FOI Bill must have been approved on Second and Third Reading.</li>
<li><strong>December 2015</strong> – The Bicameral Conference Report must have been ratified by the Senate and the House of Representatives.</li>
<li><strong>January 2016</strong> – The Enrolled People’s FOI Bill must have been presented to the President for approval.</li>
<li><strong>February 2016</strong> – The People&#8217;s FOI Bill must have been signed by the President into law.</li>
</ul>
<p>The FOI Tracker has a meter assessing Congressional action, with a green zone denoting good performance; a yellow zone denoting performance that needs improvement but still with optimistic outlook on the bill; a red zone denoting bad performance and pessimistic prognosis on the bill; and a black zone denoting that Congress is evidently out to kill the FOI Bill.</p>
<p>As of today, with the quality and integrity of the bill intact, with the Senate bill passed on Third Reading, and with the House bill well positioned for passage, Congress’s action on the FOI bill remains in the green zone.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: 20px; font-weight: bold; line-height: 1.2;">Makabayan&#8217;s unreasonable benchmark</span></p>
<p>During the plenary process, we anticipate that the Makabayan bloc will resurrect the objections it has articulated in a Position Paper submitted to the committee (See link below). These objections have centered on the exceptions that Makabayan argues could weaken the bill.</p>
<p>We agree with the answer to the Makabayan Position Paper by other authors of the FOI bill (See link below). We join their overall assessment that the consolidated bill approved by the Committee on Public Information “is a genuine and strong FOI bill that fully protects the people&#8217;s right to information while carefully balancing it with legitimate interests of individuals, the state and the bureaucracy.”</p>
<p>We add that Makabayan’s assessment that the committee report is “a greatly watered-down and weakened version” appears to be premised in part on their FOI bill, which in our humble view provides an unreasonable benchmark on exceptions. In its bill (House Bill No. 347), Makabayan advocates a near absolute right to information, and does not admit reasonable exceptions based on legitimate competing interests and rights.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 5 (a) of its bill reads:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px;"><em>“No public officer, employee or government institution falling under Section 3 hereof shall withhold public scrutiny of sources of official information or matters of public concern and interest under Section 4 hereof on the grounds of national security, public order and safety or that the information is specifically exempted from disclosure by any other statute, common law and international law principles, and pertinent jurisprudence. PROVIDED, that the sole and only exception to rule on mandatory compliance is when it is established by substantial evidence in a court proceeding that the purpose of the examination is to abet or promote or commit criminal acts defined and/or enumerated in existing statutes or to engage in sheer and idle curiosity.”</em></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">In truth, from Sweden in 1776 to Mozambique in 2014, 103 countries with a combined population of 5.8 billion pave passed FOI and access to information laws. These laws, including those in the most developed economies, invariably spell out exceptions, and appropriate remedies for citizens.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">To be sure the House Committee’s consolidated bill is not perfect when seen from differing perspectives. We appreciate the articulation of these perspectives. These will promote clarification of legislative intent in interpellation, and when merited, may result in amendments that further refine the bill either in House plenary or at the bicameral conference. The articulation of these perspectives can also assist the public in making an informed position on the emerging FOI bill.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">On our part, we are set to work for the amendment of a criminal provision in the Senate bill, if and when the bill reaches the bicameral conference stage. Section 22 (e) of the Senate version makes criminally liable “any individual who divulged or released information covered under Section 7 of this Act.” We will seek the deletion of this paragraph.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">We believe that this act is already penalized under existing law, specifically by Article 229 of the Revised Penal Code, which states:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 90px;"><em>“Article 229. Revelation of secrets by an officer. &#8211; Any public officer who shall reveal any secret known to him by reason of his official capacity, or shall wrongfully deliver papers or copies of papers of which he may have charge and which should not be published, shall suffer the penalties of prision correccional in its medium and maximum periods, perpetual special disqualification and a fine not exceeding 2,000 pesos if the revelation of such secrets or the delivery of such papers shall have caused serious damage to the public interest; otherwise, the penalties of prision correccional in its minimum period, temporary special disqualification and a fine not exceeding 50 pesos shall be imposed.” </em></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">We note that in addition to confining the application of the act to public officers, the said criminal act under Article 229 also has the required element of “damage to the public interest.” In contrast, the Senate provision penalizes mere disclosure and by any individual. We are concerned about the negative implications of this on freedom of the press and on freedom of expression.</p>
<h4>Links to the documents:</h4>
<p><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/0B6XrXh9XXl6eRkE0OGxNbTM0M1E/view?usp=sharing">House Committee Consolidated FOI Bill- 16th Congress</a></p>
<p><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/0B6XrXh9XXl6ecG9Pc2dCQ0tRQWM/view?usp=sharing">Senate Bill 1733 (3rd Reading)</a></p>
<p><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/0B6XrXh9XXl6eQkZfMVY3THA1SXc/view?usp=sharing">Makabayan position paper on FOI TWG Report</a></p>
<p><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/0B6XrXh9XXl6eZXdJY2pyMEpsTFk/view?usp=sharing">Answer to Makabayan objections on FOI</a></p>
<h4>Signed:</h4>
<h5>Organizations</h5>
<p>Atty. Nepomuceno Malaluan<br />
Co-Director, Institute for Freedom of Information (IFOI)</p>
<p>Most Rev. Rolando J. Tria Tirona, OCD, DD<br />
National Director, CBCP-National Secretariat for Social Action, Justice and Peace (CBCP-NASSA)</p>
<p>Ms. Malou Mangahas<br />
Executive Director, Philippine Center for Investigative Journalism (PCIJ)</p>
<p>Ms. Melinda Quintos de Jesus<br />
Executive Director, Center for Media Freedom &amp; Responsibility</p>
<p>Mr. Peter Angelo V. Perfecto<br />
Executive Director, Makati Business Club</p>
<p>Mr. Josua Mata<br />
Secretary General, Sentro ng mga Nagkakaisa at Progresibong Manggagawa (SENTRO)</p>
<p>Atty. Eirene Jhone Aguila<br />
Aksyong Kabayanihan Para sa Organisadong Pagbabago (ANGKOP)</p>
<p>Atty. Roberto Eugenio Cadiz<br />
Executive Director, Libertas</p>
<p>Mr. Vincent Lazatin<br />
Executive Director, Transparency and Accountability Network (TAN)</p>
<p>Ms. Rowena C. Paraan<br />
Chairperson, National Union of Journalists of the Philippines (NUJP)</p>
<p>Ms. Jenina Joy Chavez<br />
Coordinator, Action for Economic Reforms Industrial Policy Team (AER-IP Team)</p>
<p>Mr. Ariel Sebellino<br />
Executive Director, Philippine Press Institute (PPI)</p>
<p>Anthony Leachon, MD, FPCP, PACP<br />
President, Philippine College of Physicians</p>
<p>Mr. Elso Cabangon<br />
Filipino Migrant Workers Group</p>
<p>Mr. Allan Pangilinan; Mr. Ryan Nicolas<br />
Conveners, FOI Youth Initiative (FYI)</p>
<p>Mr. Sixto Donato Macasaet<br />
Executive Director, CODE-NGO</p>
<p>Mr. Isagani Serrano<br />
President, Philippine Rural Reconstruction Movement (PRRM)</p>
<p>Mr. Rolando Ocampo<br />
Prudentialife Warriors Pilipinas</p>
<p>Mr. Joseph Purugganan<br />
Coordinator, Focus on the Global South &#8211; Philippines Programme</p>
<p>Mr. Norman Cabrera<br />
Ang Kapatiran Party<br />
Ms. Ellene Sana<br />
Executive Director, Center for Migrant Advocacy (CMA)</p>
<p>Ms. Annie Enriquez-Geron<br />
President, Public Services Labor Independent Confederation (PSLINK)</p>
<p>Mr. Walter Balane<br />
Bukidnon Network of Editors and Writers for Social Change (Bukidnon NEWS)</p>
<p>Mr. Gerry F. Rivera<br />
President, PAL Employees Association (PALEA)</p>
<p>Mr. Narciso P. Jover Jr.<br />
Executive Director, Tri-People Concern for Peace, Progress and Development of Mindanao (TRICOM), Inc.</p>
<p>Mr. Renato Magtubo<br />
Chairperson, Partido Manggagawa (PM)</p>
<p>Mr. Raul Socrates C. Banzuela<br />
National Coordinator, Pambansang Kilusan ng mga Samahang Magsasaka (PAKISAMA)</p>
<p>Mr. Max M. de Mesa<br />
Chairperson, Philippine Alliance of Human Rights Advocates (PAHRA)</p>
<p>Ms. Merci Angeles<br />
Executive Director, Peace Women Partners Inc.</p>
<p>Atty. Corazon Valdez Fabros<br />
STOP the War Coalition Philippines</p>
<p>Ms. Trinidad Domingo<br />
Spokesperson, Save Agrarian Reform Alliance</p>
<p>Mr. Red Batario, Executive Director; Ms. Adelina Sevilla Alvarez, Program Director<br />
Center for Community Journalism and Development (CCJD)</p>
<p>Mr. Sammy Gamboa<br />
Secretary General, Freedom from Debt Coalition</p>
<h5>Individuals</h5>
<p>Atty. Lorenzo R. Tañada III                                                                             Former Deputy Speaker, House of Representatives</p>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5;">Dr. Wilfrido Villacorta<br />
Member, 1986 Constitutional Commission<br />
(Co-sponsor of the Right to Information) </span></p>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5;">Prof. Edna E. A. Co                                                                                          </span><span style="line-height: 1.5;">Executive Director, UP Center for Integrative and Development Studies</span></p>
<p>Nicole Curato, Ph.D.<br />
Research Fellow, Centre for Deliberative Democracy &amp; Global Governance<br />
University of Canberra</p>
<p>Sylvia Estrada Claudio, MD, PhD<br />
Professor, Department of Women and Development Studies, College of Social Work and Community Development, University of the Philippines.</p>
<p>Prof. Aileen San Pablo-Baviera<br />
Asian Center, University of the Philippines</p>
<p>Ms. Ma. Aurora Quilala;</p>
<p>Ms. Reylynne Dela Paz</p>
<h6></h6>
<ul style="display: none;">
<li>05-12-2015</li>
<li>85</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://i-foi.org/performance-tracker/congress-foi-performance-tracker-1/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>

<!-- Dynamic page generated in 8.724 seconds. -->
<!-- Cached page generated by WP-Super-Cache on 2015-08-21 13:21:08 -->
